Guide to the Joseph Conrad Papers, 1850-1972 RL.00256
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Joseph Conrad papers
1850-1972
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Conrad, Joseph, 1857-1924
RL.00256
3 Linear Feet
Collection contains letters and scrapbooks about the life and works of Joseph Conrad. Correspondence includes letters by Conrad to David S. Meldrum, an advisor to Wm. Blackwood & Sons. Conrad discusses family news, including his son Borys, as well as his various literary projects, including Lord Jim, Heart of Darkness, Youth: A Narrative and Other Tales, and The Rescue. Other correspondence includes letters from Conrad to Sir Sidney Colvin and his wife, Frances; Henry Arthur Jones and his daughter, Jennie Doris Arthur Jones Thorne; and T. Fisher Unwin, Conrad's publisher. There is also an album of photographs, 1860-1890, of Conrad's Polish relatives, and scrapbooks, 6 vols., compiled by Conrad's wife, Jessie George Conrad, with clippings, reviews, and tributes.
202 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Joseph Conrad Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift, 1949-1968. The bulk of this collection was acquired by Duke Professor William M. Blackburn, a Conrad scholar who purchased the letters from David S. Meldrum's daughter in 1958.
Biographical Note
British author, of Bishopsbourne, Kent, England. Originally from Poland. Author of Heart of Darkness, Lord Jim, Nostromo, The Secret Agent, Youth: A Narrative and Two Other Stories, The Rescue, and many other novels and stories. He married his wife, Jessie George, in 1896; the couple had two sons, Borys and John.
Collection Overview
Collection contains letters and scrapbooks about the life and works of Joseph Conrad. Materials have been sorted into 4 series: Letters from Joseph Conrad; Letters from Jessie Conrad (Joseph Conrad's wife); Clippings and Ephemera; and Scrapbooks and Album. The 2 correspondence series consist of letters from Joseph and Jessie to others, including literary contacts and personal friends. The bulk of Joseph Conrad's letters are written to David S. Meldrum, an advisor to Wm. Blackwood & Sons. Conrad discusses family news, including the activities of his son Borys in World War I, as well as progress on his various literary projects. Titles mentioned over the course of his correspondence with Meldrum include Lord Jim, Heart of Darkness, Youth: A Narrative and Other Tales, and The Rescue. Other correspondence includes letters from Conrad to Sir Sidney Colvin and his wife, Frances; Henry Arthur Jones and his daughter, Jennie Doris Arthur Jones Thorne; and T. Fisher Unwin, Conrad's publisher. Most of Jessie Conrad's letters date from after Joseph Conrad's death, and relate to the publication of her memoir of him and royalties from the publication of his papers. The Clippings and Ephemera Series includes clippings contemporary to Conrad's life, reviews of his works, and articles about his legacy. There is also an information folder about the provenance of the Conrad Papers collection at Duke, other Conrad reference materials, and assorted printed ephemera. The collection's volumes are held in the Scrapbooks and Album series. There is an album of photographs, 1860-1890, of Conrad's Polish relatives, and scrapbooks, 6 vols., compiled by Conrad's wife, Jessie George Conrad, with clippings, reviews, and tributes. Portions of the scrapbooks relate to Jessie Conrad's cookbook, "A Handbook of Cookery for a Small House," and her memoir of Joseph Conrad, "Joseph Conrad as I Knew Him" (1926). There is also a scrapbook about Joseph Conrad's tour of the United States in 1923.
United States -- Description and travel; World War, 1914-1918 -- France; Authors and publishers; Authors, English; Authors -- Correspondence; Scrapbooks; Colvin, Sidney, Sir, 1845-1927; Colvin, Frances, Lady; Conrad, Jessie; Conrad, Borys, 1898-1979; Thorne, Jennie Doris Arthur Jones; Unwin, T. Fisher, (Thomas Fisher), 1848-1935; Blackwood, William, 1836-1912; Jellicoe, John Rushworth Jellicoe, Earl, 1859-1935; Jean-Aubry, G., (Georges), 1882-1950 -- Joseph Conrad; Jones, Henry Arthur, 1851-1929; Conrad, Joseph, 1857-1924; Conrad, Joseph, 1857-1924 -- Monuments; James, Henry, 1843-1916; Galsworthy, John, 1867-1933; Meldrum, David Storrar, 1865-
- Letters from Joseph Conrad, 1897-1922
  - Blackwood, William (Blackwood and Sons), 1899-1900 (Box 1)
  - Colvin, Lady Frances Jane, 1920 (Box 1)
  - Colvin, Sidney, 1904-1919 (Box 1)
  - Meldrum, David S., 1897-1908; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Unknown recipients, 1908, 1922 (Box 1)
  - Unwin, T. Fisher, 1897 (Box 1)
  - Thorne, Jennie Doris Arthur Jones, 1919-1920 (Box 1)
- Letters from Jessie Conrad, 1909-1936
  - Hodgson and Co., 1924, 1936 (Box 1)
  - Meldrum, David S., 1909-1910 (Box 1)
  - Unknown recipients, 1935 (Box 1)
- Clippings and Ephemera, 1898-1971
  - Information folder about the collection, 1958-1971 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings and reviews of Conrad's writings, 1898-1903 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous clippings about Conrad's life and writings, 1923-1965 (Box 1)
  - Photocopies of clippings about Conrad's life, from other sources, 1923-1969 (Box 1)
  - Printed ephemera, 1903 and undated (Box 1)
  - Empty envelopes, 1922 and undated (Box 1)
- Scrapbooks and Album, 1861-1972; 7 Volumes 7 volumes; 1 folder.
  - Joseph Conrad photograph album of his Polish relatives, 1850s-1860s (Box 2)
  - Captions and duplicates of Joseph Conrad's photograph album of his Polish relatives, 1970s (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook I: Joseph Teador Korzeniowski Conrad (Reviews during his American tour, 227 pgs.), 1923 (Box 5)
  - Scrapbook II: Reviews of Literary Career of Joseph Conrad (71 pgs.), 1924 (Box 4)
  - Scrapbook IV: Reviews of Joseph Conrad as I Knew Him, by Jessie Conrad, 1926 (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook III: A Handbook of Cookery for a Small House, by Jessie Conrad (67 pgs.), 1923 (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook V: Criticisms of Joseph Conrad: His Life and Letters (by G. Jean-Aubry), and Memorial Cullings (77 pgs.), 1927 (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook VI: Reviews of Joseph Conrad and His Circle, by Jessie Conrad (67 pgs.), 1926 (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Jessie Conrad's book was published as Joseph Conrad As I Knew Him.